William Edgar Borah Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William Edgar Borah Papers 1905-1940 1912-1940
MSS13276
Borah, William Edgar, 1865-1940
260,000 items
880 containers plus 2 oversize
352.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer and United States senator from Idaho. Correspondence, memoranda, reports, subject and legislative files, speeches and articles, patronage and constituent files, notebooks, newspaper clippings, and other material relating primarily to Borah's political interests and career in the Senate.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Addams, Jane, 1860-1935--Correspondence.; Borah, William Edgar, 1865-1940.; Borchard, Edwin, 1884-1951--Correspondence.; Dawes, Henry M. (Henry May), 1877-1952--Correspondence.; Dyer, Leonidas Carstarphen, 1871-1957--Correspondence.; Evans, Evan A., 1876- --Correspondence.; Fish, Hamilton, II, 1849-1936--Correspondence.; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924--Correspondence.; Gooding, Frank Robert, 1859-1928--Correspondence.; Hapgood, Norman, 1868-1937--Correspondence.; Hart, John W., 1866-1935--Correspondence.; Hawley, James H. (James Henry), 1847-1929--Correspondence.; Hays, Will H. (Will Harrison), 1879-1954--Correspondence.; Hileman, Grace. Grace Hileman correspondence. 1923-1936.; Holmes, John Haynes, 1879-1964--Correspondence.; Johnson, James Weldon, 1871-1938--Correspondence.; Kellogg, Frank B. (Frank Billings), 1856-1937--Correspondence.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944--Correspondence.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924--Correspondence.; McKaig, Ray, 1880-1962--Correspondence.; Pinchot, Amos, 1873-1944--Correspondence.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946--Correspondence.; Robins, Raymond, 1873-1954--Correspondence.; Rockwell, Irvin E. (Irvin Elmer), 1862-1952--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Walsh, Thomas Joseph, 1873-1952--Correspondence.; White, William Allen, 1868-1944--Correspondence.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924--Correspondence.
Organizations
League of Nations.; Permanent Court of International Justice.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); United States. Army.; United States. Congress. Senate.; United States. National Recovery Administration.
Subjects
Agriculture.; Antitrust law.; Communism--United States.; Constitutional law--United States.; Constitutions--United States.; Disarmament.; Draft--United States.; Internal security--United States.; International cooperation.; Isolationism--United States.; Land use--United States.; Neutrality--United States.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Patronage, Political--United States.; Peace.; Presidential candidates--United States.; Presidents--United States--Election--1936.; Sino-Japanese War, 1937-1945.; War.
Places
Idaho--Politics and government.; Latin America--History, Military.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; Turkey--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Economic policy--1933-1945.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations--Turkey.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.
Titles
Treaty of Lausanne (1923)
Occupations
Lawyers.; Senators, U.S. Congress--Idaho.
Acquisition Information
The papers of William Edgar Borah, United States senator from Idaho, were given to the Library of Congress by his wife, Mary McConnell Borah in 1940. Additional material was received by gift and purchase from various sources, 1941-1959.
Related Material
A collection of Borah papers at the Idaho State Historical Society treats his law practice and political activities from 1890 to 1907, and a collection of scrapbooks at the University of Idaho Library covers the period 1904-1940. A microfilm copy of the scrapbooks is held by the Library of Congress.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William Edgar Borach are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1865, June 29 Born, Jasper Township, near Fairfield, Ill.
1885 1887 Attended University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kans.
1887 Admitted to the Kansas bar
1890 Settled in Boise, Idaho; practiced law
1895 Married Mary McConnell
1896 Ran for the House of Representatives on the Silver-Republican ticket
1903 Ran for the United States Senate
1907 Elected to the United States Senate from Idaho Prosecutor in the trial of William Dudley (“Big Bill”) Haywood, socialist labor leader charged with murder
1919 1920 Opposed entry of the United States into the League of Nations
1923 Introduced first of several Senate resolutions to outlaw war
1924 Succeeded Henry Cabot Lodge as chairman, Senate Committee on Foreign Relations
1928 1929 Led fight in Senate for Kellogg-Briand peace pact
1936 Candidate, Republican Party nomination for president
1940 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Edgar Borah (1865-1940) span the period 1905-1940, with the bulk of the material from 1912-1940. The collection constitutes the record of his career in the Senate, which began in 1907 and ended with his death in 1940, at the midpoint of his sixth consecutive term. The papers cover virtually every aspect of Borah's political life and include extensive files on antitrust legislation, constitutional interpretation, and foreign policy. There is little in the collection about his youth or his career as an attorney in Idaho, and most of his Senate office files for the years from 1907 to 1912 were destroyed when his office was moved from the basement of the Capitol to the Senate office building. A collection of Borah papers at the Idaho State Historical Society treats his law practice and political activities from 1890 to 1907, and a collection of scrapbooks at the University of Idaho Library covers the period 1904-1940. A microfilm copy of the scrapbooks is held by the Library of Congress.
The General Office File, the largest series, is organized by subject and correspondent within twelve-month increments. Files on politics, Russia, disarmament, and agriculture reveal the range of Borah's interests, although files that appear to be commonplace, such as invitations and requests for speeches, often contain significant correspondence on substantive issues. Significant topical categories include files titled "documents," containing correspondence with constituents concerning government publications; "newspapers," referring to articles in newspapers and periodicals on Borah; and "manuscripts," relating to papers sent to Borah by authors seeking assistance in publishing their work.
The World Court, the League of Nations, military activities in Latin America, routine army matters, legislation, politics, the Red Scare, universal military training, and Russia are topics that dominate the General Office File from the World War I era to the Depression. Among the principal themes in the papers from the 1920s are Borah's attempts to secure American recognition of the Soviet Union, his support of measures that would outlaw war, and his reactions to domestic political and economical unrest. Material relating to Franklin D. Roosevelt, the New Deal, and the National Recovery Administration take up an increasingly larger portion of the files during the 1930s, as do subjects such as China's war with Japan, the Lausanne Settlement, and neutrality legislation.
Correspondents upon whom Borah relied for advice on state and local political issues include Evan Evans, James H. Gipson, Frank Robert Gooding, John W. Hart, James H. Hawley, Ray McKaig, and Irvin E. Rockwell. Files on topics such as politics, antilynching, Russia, the Justice Department, treaties, and the World Court include correspondence with Jane Addams, Edwin Borchard, Henry M. Dawes, Leonidas Carstarphen Dyer, Hamilton Fish, Samuel Gompers, Norman Hapgood, Will H. Hays, John Haynes Holmes, James Weldon Johnson, Frank B. Kellogg, Frank Knox, Henry Cabot Lodge, Amos Pinchot, Gifford Pinchot, Raymond Robins, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Thomas Joseph Walsh, William Allen White, and Woodrow Wilson.
The Subject File contains material on a wide variety of topics, although most of it relates to Borah's specific legislative and political interests. Included are important files pertaining to treaties, appointments, Department of State budgets, and the major problems of American foreign policy in the era between the two world wars. The Subject File complements the Public Opinion File, which contains letters from the public on matters such as neutrality legislation, the World Court, the embargo of Spain, and New Deal reform efforts.
The Speeches, Statements, and Articles File is perhaps the most comprehensive series for exploring Borah's positions on public issues, for his attitudes are documented more thoroughly in his speeches and public statements than in his characteristically terse correspondence. Borah regarded public speaking and debate as a critical ingredient of public life. His speeches, press releases, and public statements were prepared with meticulous care, and many of the research materials that formed the basis of his speeches are organized in subject files within this series.
Borah's activities in behalf of Idaho constituents are documented throughout the collection, but four series representing major aspects of constituent casework are particularly salient for understanding this feature of his career. The Pension File and Veterans Claims File deal exclusively with the problem of individual constituents; the Patronage File and Land Utilization File contain materials relating to broad social and political matters as well as assistance to individuals. The Land Utilization File ranges from applications for homesteads to research materials for legislation pertaining to the public domain. Many of the constituent requests in these files were merely routed to the appropriate executive agency for attention, but Borah occasionally noted his recommendations and policy judgements when transmitting a request.
The Borah for President Committee series illustrates the steps taken by a small coterie of loyal admirers to obtain the 1936 Republican presidential nomination for Borah. Much of the correspondence consists of exchanges between Carl G. Bachmann, chairman of the committee, and various contributors to the campaign. Rounding out the collection is a small group of correspondence and other papers of Grace Hileman, Borah's secretary. The correspondence, largely personal in nature, touches on matters of interest to Borah.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in twelve series:
General Office File, 1907-1940
Land Utilization File, 1909-1935
Patronage File, 1908-1940
Pension File
Veterans Claims File
Public Opinion File, 1925-1939
Subject File, 1905-1940
Speeches, Statements, and Articles, 1908-1939
Stenographic and Personal Notebooks, 1920-1939
Miscellany
Borah for President Committee Papers, 1935-1936
Correspondence of Grace Hileman, 1923-1936
Container List
- General Office File, 1907-1940 (Box 1-528)
  Letters received and carbons of letters sent, memoranda, reports, newspaper clippings, legislative bills, and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged chronologically in twelve-month increments beginning in December of one year and ending in November of the following year, from 1909 to 1934. After 1934, the files follow the more traditional calendar-year period. Within each period, the files are arranged alphabetically by name or subject and chronologically by month therein. This file is a composite of six former files: Correspondence, Departmental, General, Independent Offices, New Deal Correspondence, and Political Correspondence.
  - 1907-1909 (Box 1)
    - A-Eaton, R.H., (7 folders)
    - Echlins, Henry M.- Lilly, Cephas, (8 folders) (Box 2)
    - Lincoln County National Bank-Sharelear, Joe H., (8 folders) (Box 3)
    - Sharp, J. W.-Zipper, C. H., (8 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1909-1910, Idaho
  - 1912-1913
    - Applications for pardons
    - Letters of introduction
    - Miscellaneous
  - 1913-1914 (Box 5)
    - Agricultural Capital Act, (2 folders)
    - Agriculture Department
    - Alabama
    - Alaskan matters
    - Annapolis, Md., United States Naval Academy
    - Applications for pardons
    - Applications for positions
      - A-N, (4 folders)
      - O-Z (Box 6)
    - Appointments
    - Arizona
    - Army matters
    - Assay office
    - Boise barracks, Boise, Idaho
    - Borah, Charles F.
    - Business and financial, (3 folders)
    - California
    - Charity
    - Children's Bureau
    - Citizenship
    - Civil Service
    - Claims, (1 folder) (Box 7)
    - Colorado
    - Congratulations
    - Congressional Record
    - Connecticut
    - Consular Service
    - Currency bill
    - Delaware
    - Dewey, Edward H.
    - District of Columbia matters
    - Documents
    - Educational institutions
    - Federal buildings
    - Federal courts
    - Federal district courts
    - Fish, applications for (Box 8)
    - Florida
    - Foreign Relations Committee
    - General information
    - Good roads
    - Hawley, James H.
    - Idaho
      - A-Z miscellaneous, (5 folders)
      - Balderston, William
      - Burrell, E. A.
      - Fisk, Fred
      - Gooding, Frank Robert (Box 9)
      - Hart, John W.
      - Lingenfelter, C. H.
      - Lisle, C. J.
      - Peterson, J. H.
      - Purcell, L. I.
      - Rockwell, Irvin E.
      - Wyman, Frank T.
    - Illinois
    - Immigration
    - Indian affairs
    - Indiana
    - Industrial Relations Commission
    - Insular matters
    - Interstate Commerce Commission
    - Invitations, (1 folder) (Box 10)
    - Iowa
    - Kansas
    - Kentucky
    - Labor matters
      - Colorado
      - General, (2 folders)
    - Lasley, Sue
    - Legislation, miscellaneous, (2 folders)
    - Letters of introduction
    - Lincoln farm memorial, Hodgenville, Ky.
    - Liquor legislation, (2 folders)
    - Louisiana (Box 11)
    - McConnel, E. A.
    - McConnell, William J.
    - Maine
    - Maryland
    - Massachusetts
    - Merchant marine
    - Mexican affairs
    - Michigan
    - Minnesota
    - Miscellaneous, (5 folders); (1 folder) (Box 12)
    - Missouri
    - Montana
    - National banks
    - Naval affairs
    - Nevada
    - New Hampshire
    - New Jersey
    - New Mexico
    - New York, (2 folders)
    - North Carolina
    - North Dakota
    - Ohio
    - Oklahoma
    - Oregon
    - Panama Canal, (2 folders)
    - Parcel post (Box 13)
    - Patents
    - Pennsylvania
    - Pension legislation
    - Perkins, George W.
    - Postal laws
    - Public health
    - Publications
    - Railway matters
    - Requests for photographs
    - Requests for speeches
    - Reserve banks
    - Rhode Island
    - Rivers and harbors, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Rural credits, (2 folders)
    - Shires, Joseph A.
    - Social
    - South Dakota
    - State Department
    - Speed test bill, (2 folders)
    - Tariff
    - Tennessee
    - Texas
    - Timber fraud cases (Box 15)
    - Treaties, (2 folders)
    - Trusts
      - General, (3 folders)
      - Clayton bill
      - Trade Commission bill
    - U.S. district attorney
    - U.S. Marshall
    - Virginia
    - War tax matters
    - Washington
    - Washington, D.C.
    - West Point, N.Y., United States Military academy (Box 16)
    - West Virginia
    - West Virginia conditions
    - Wilson, Edgar
    - Wisconsin
    - Woman suffrage, (3 folders)
    - Wyoming
  - 1914-1915
    - Agricultural capital bill
    - Agriculture Department
    - Alaska
    - Applications for pardons, (4 folders)
    - Applications for positions, A-W, (3 folders) (Box 17)
    - Appointments
    - Arms and ammunition
    - Army matters
    - Boise barracks, Boise, Idaho
    - Borah, Charles F.
    - Business and financial, (3 folders)
    - California
    - Charity
    - Citizenship
    - Claims
    - Commission on Industrial Relations
    - Congratulations
    - Congressional Record
    - Consular positions
    - Damper, E. R. (Box 18)
    - Documents
    - Federal buildings
    - Federal courts
    - Federal Reserve Act
    - Fish, applications for
    - Frank, Leo, case
    - General information
    - Idaho
      - A-Z miscellaneous, (6 folders)
      - Dewey, Edward H.
      - Gipson, James H.
      - Hart, John W.
      - Purcell, L. I.
      - Rockwell, Irvin E.
      - University of Idaho, Moscow, Idaho
    - Illinois (Box 19)
    - Immigration
    - Indian affairs
    - Indiana
    - Insular affairs
    - Interstate Commerce Commission
    - Invitations
      - General
      - California-Minnesota, (14 folders)
      - Missouri-Washington, (15 folders) (Box 20)
    - Iowa
    - Kansas
    - Kentucky
    - Labor
    - Land Office patronage
    - Legislation, miscellaneous, (2 folders)
    - Letters of introduction
    - Lincoln farm memorial, Hodgenville, Ky.
    - Liquor legislation (Box 21)
    - McConnell, William J.
    - Maine
    - Maryland
    - Massachusetts
    - Merchant marine
    - Mexican affairs
    - Michigan
    - Minnesota
    - Miscellaneous
    - Missouri
    - Montana
    - National banks
    - National preparedness
    - Naval academy, Annapolis, Md.
    - Naval affairs
    - Nebraska
    - Nevada
    - New Hampshire
    - New Jersey
    - New York
    - Newspapers, (2 folders) (Box 22)
    - North Carolina
    - North Dakota
    - Ohio
    - Oklahoma
    - Oregon
    - Panama Canal
    - Passports
    - Patents
    - Pennsylvania
    - Pension legislation
    - Photographs, requests for
    - Postal laws
      - General
      - Rural carriers
      - Stamped envelopes
    - Post Office Department
    - Preparedness
    - President's speech with constituents, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Railway matters
    - Religious matters
    - Rivers and harbors
    - Rural credits
    - Social
    - Soldiers Home, Washington, D.C., admission to
    - South Dakota
    - Speed test bill
    - State Department, (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - State matters
    - Tariff
    - Tennessee
    - Texas
    - Treaties
    - Trusts
    - Utah
    - Vandivert, S. W.
    - Virginia
    - War matters
    - War matters, embargo
    - Washington (state)
    - Washington, D.C.
    - West Point, N.Y., United States Military academy
    - Wisconsin
    - Woman suffrage
    - Worth, D.
    - Wyoming
  - 1915-1916 (Box 25)
    - Agricultural capital bill
    - Agriculture Department
    - Alabama
    - Alaska
    - Applications for pardons
    - Applications for positions, (3 folders)
    - Arizona
    - Army matters, (4 folders)
    - Assay office
    - Borah, C. F.
    - Business and financial, (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - Charity
    - Citizenship, (3 folders)
    - Claims, (3 folders)
    - Commission on Industrial Relations
    - Congressional Record
    - Consular positions
    - District of Columbia matters
    - Documents, (3 folders) (Box 27)
    - Educational matters
    - Federal
      - Buildings
      - Courts, (2 folders)
      - Prisons
      - Trade Commission
    - Fish, applications for
    - Florida
    - General information
    - Georgia
    - Good roads
    - High cost of living
    - Idaho (Box 28)
      - A-Z miscellaneous, (8 folders)
      - Austin, Mark
      - Barker, George
      - Burrell, E. A.
      - Cavanah, Charles C.
      - Dewey, Edward H., (2 folders)
      - Flenner, Guy
      - Gipson, James H.
      - Hart, John W.
      - Hodgin, Shad L. (Box 29)
      - Purcell, L. I.
      - Rockwell, Irvin E.
    - Illinois
    - Immigration, child labor bill
    - Income tax
    - Indian affairs
    - Indiana
    - Interstate commerce
    - Invitations
      - Colorado-Nebraska, (16 folders)
      - New York-West Virginia, (14 folders) (Box 30)
    - Labor matters, (2 folders)
    - Lasley, A. M.
    - Legislation, miscellaneous, (2 folders)
    - Letters of recommendation and introduction
    - Lincoln farm memorial, Hodgenville, Ky.
    - Louisiana
    - Maine
    - Maryland
    - Merchant marine
    - Mexican matters, (3 folders) (Box 31)
    - Michigan
    - Mining station
    - Miscellaneous, (2 folders)
    - Missouri
    - Monnett, F. S.
    - National banks
    - National convention
    - National Guard
    - Naval academy, Annapolis, Md., (2 folders) (Box 32)
    - Naval affairs
    - Newspapers and magazines
    - Panama Canal employees
    - Parcel post
    - Passports
    - Patents
    - Pension legislation
    - Philippines
    - Politics
      - California-Massachusetts, (7 folders)
      - Montana-Wyoming, (21 folders) (Box 33)
    - Post Office Department, (2 folders)
    - Preparedness, (4 folders) (Box 34)
    - Preparedness, militia bill, (3 folders)
    - Price fixing bill
    - Prohibition
    - Public health (Box 35)
    - Railway mail pay
    - Railway matters
    - Reclamation report
    - Religious matters
    - Requests for photographs
    - Requests for speeches
    - Rivers and harbors
    - Rural credit bill, (2 folders)
    - Sheep experiment farm
    - Social
    - Soldier's home, admission to
    - State matters (Box 36)
    - Strike matters
    - Tariff
    - Treaties
    - Trusts
    - University of Idaho, Moscow, Idaho
    - War matters
      - Armed merchant vessels
      - Miscellaneous, (2 folders)
    - War tax
    - West Point, N.Y., United States Military academy, (2 folders)
    - Woman suffrage
  - 1916-1917 (Box 37)
    - Agriculture Department
    - Applications for pardons
    - Applications for positions, (4 folders)
    - Army matters
      - General, (2 folders)
      - Discharges
    - Borah, Charles T. (Box 38)
    - Burrell, E. A.
    - Business and financial, (2 folders)
    - Censorship
    - Charity
    - Citizenship
    - Claims
    - Commission on Industrial Relations
    - Committee on Indian Depredations
    - Congratulations
    - Congressional Record
    - Consular positions
    - Dewey, Edward H. (Box 39)
    - District of Columbia matters
    - Documents
    - Educational matters
    - Elliott, Henry W.
    - Espionage law
    - Evans, Evan
    - Federal buildings
    - Federal courts
    - Federal farm loans
    - Federal judges
    - Federal prisons
    - Fish
    - Food Administration
      - General, (2 folders)
      - Wheat
    - Food control
    - Food question
    - Foreign affairs (Box 40)
    - Fuel Administration
    - General information
    - Gipson, James H.
    - Good roads
    - Gooding, Frank Robert
    - Hart, John W.
    - Hawley, Jesse
    - High cost of living
    - Immigration
    - Income tax
    - Indian affairs
    - Inquiries
    - Internal Revenue
    - Interstate Commerce Commission
    - Invitations
      - California-Illinois, (8 folders)
      - Indiana-Wisconsin, (20 folders) (Box 41)
    - Japanese question
    - Kettenbach, William E.
    - Labor matters
    - Legislation, miscellaneous
    - Letters of recommendation
    - Lisle, Charles J.
    - McConnell, William J. (Box 42)
    - Mail clerk salaries
    - Mexican matters
    - Miscellaneous, (2 folders)
    - Nampa Railway postal clerks matter
    - National banks
    - National Guard, (2 folders)
    - Naval academy, Annapolis, Md.
    - Navy matters
      - General
      - Discharges
    - Newspapers
    - Parcel post (Box 43)
    - Passports
    - Patents
    - Peace resolution, (2 folders)
    - Pension legislation
    - Personal
    - Politics
    - Postal laws
    - Preparedness, (2 folders) (Box 44)
    - Prohibition, (3 folders)
    - Purcell, L. I.
    - Railway mail service
    - Railway matters
    - Red Cross
    - Requests for photographs and autographs, (1 folder)
    - Revenue bill, (2 folders) (Box 45)
    - Rivers and harbors
    - Rockwell, Irvin E.
    - Rural credits